hi thanks everyone
it's Fourth of July 2023
and we're in our second
discussion on chapter seven so
we'll head back over there
does anyone want to
type a question
or
add any reflection or thought or just
question or area they want to look at
today
okay well I I could say something right
there yeah please
um so I last time I joined was four
weeks ago and I was saying about
um
well I was advocating having python code
for
um as as examples
I I went away and just coded up
um
the bits
at the very beginning of chapter seven
um of the notes or the musical notes
which was sort of transferring
well
converting the text into python with his
comments it it didn't really get me
well it it showed the reasons why the
matrices contain the numbers that they
did it didn't really say
much more than that but then I've I've
just discovered appendix C in the book
um and in a way that goes through
uh something
similar uh although it doesn't explain
the matrices the precise numbers in each
matrices
in uh quite so explicit way
uh and then in later on in chapter seven
there's the uh the maze example and
again that these are all
filling in with the application but then
it's it's throwing it's just formatting
the data to the point where it can then
be given to
um an spm-12
function yeah so mdp
there without
so I would like to see
what's inside there and then be able to
graph
um
for example various metrics like uh
equations things
like Mutual information
um novelty
uh
all of to to help get an intuitive
feel
um I think appendix C says about so
being able to play around with the
numbers
get an intuitive understanding but I
I want to see more than just
laying around with the the matrices
um
the inputs
so yeah so it's just an update on on
where I am really
thank you yeah appendix C is very sparse
um
and it doesn't
um I mean I
they would have done well potentially to
have just simply provided the
reproducibility code for each
figure
without interspersing it with plain text
because then it's kind of this reverse
engineering process but but what you
said is absolutely
um right on which is
the entire
pomdp the entire figure 4.3
discrete time model
it's all the letters that we talk about
a b c d
and then e which is just given the
letter V here
and then the true starting condition
and then
then you just let it run
now here's the SPM mdp vbx variational
base
um X I'm sure exactly what the x is
but I I've heard that this is sort of a
like
um
not inscrutable
but it's not simple to to translate this
function just straightforwardly to
python
which is one reason why um like many
people do can continue using the um
the Matlab variant
because this contains a lot of like
accelerated methods that are uh and it
contains like a lot of extra bells and
whistles to generate the figures and so
that makes it quite easy but in general
it speaks to exactly what chapter six
highlights which is that octave
inference modeling is about
representing the agent in the
environment
and then the methods for for letting the
agent come to its own Solutions
are straightforward
rather than needing to do a secondary
and at some computational scale yes
um further techniques are needed
but to a first approximation the work of
understanding a system of Interest
is in exactly specifying the
dimensionality of the matrices
same as in pi mdp in model stream 7.
but yeah how was it I mean what did you
see the matrices any differently or
think about the the
models any differently
no what I what I carried up it was was
really just what to to get an idea of
how things might be coded up and this
wasn't to have something that was
certainly not anything that was
simulation efficient it was something
very clumsy so for example what you're
showing there
with the B Matrix
um
it would be
explaining why why the 97s are there
um in those particular places
so starting off with a what an all zeros
Matrix or maybe you know ones in this
case
and uh
and it was it's normalized there but um
so so that you can you're then
describe in The Matrix B directly in
terms of the the application you don't
need the separate
bits of text just just to explain what
there is there
so I think I think that was helpful
um
what would be helpful as part of the
wider
uh if if that was taken to completion
and possibly the team A's one could be
taken
further
um and would have been more useful
yeah
but but yeah it's it's
for me it's it's getting inside
those those functions to see what's see
what's going on
um
because I don't have any
any real feel so yes I'd like to be able
to see what his his free energy changing
as as various things happen
um
and it's comprised of these different
factors or it can be interpreted in this
different way
so that you can then
play around with the numbers say to put
it into a position where there is is
novelty and you can see the
um
the uh the aspects the term of free
energy that's described as novelty and
see the effect on that
so
I think that would give me of a much
better feeling rather than you know this
[Music]
um
the SPM 12 is is just a black box
solution
yeah
yeah cool and if and if you want to we
can post on the
textbook group
um
repo
so maybe we can then use it and
um
you know chapter seven eventually have
every single
example
potentially even in multiple languages
but sorted like according to the
numbering of the textbook
so at the end of
code two I I that was I put some
comments of you know I'd be interested
in setting or be involved in a group
that was basically Doom I've I've said
uh well to to unpick
um pi mdp
and someone made a comment of well you
could just code up equations
um that are in the book and maybe maybe
that's the right approach
um
because I've I've looked into SPM 12 and
the data structures in there are just
horrendously complicated
really
um so trying to get into that would be
you know would be very difficult
um but maybe just building up from the
equations in the book would be a
would be manageable
or
thank you
um
anyone else want to bring up anything or
ask anything or we can look at the
questions
okay not I don't remember exactly which
ones we may have addressed um last time
but
um okay okay that's
What's Happening Here
logged in under a difference
okay
those are the thumbs up
then you had to be there okay
um
what do the rows columns and numbers
mean in equation 7.2
to check your understanding could you
design another B Matrix that could be
used in the music example or another
example
so the simple answer is
each cell
represents the probability of moving
from a row to a column
and these are the notes one two three
four
with this one over a hundred so that
summing across
you get
um one
um this musician it has a 97 percent
accuracy
um correctness in in moving forward
through this song
and uh as we look towards what kinds of
like questions and variants would help
us deepen understanding
like
what would it look like to be more
accurate well there'd be a 98
or what would it look like if the third
note
to the fourth note was really hard
or what would it look like if there was
five notes
or
um write a 12 tone composition
using 12 notes
but anyone else want to have any
comments or thoughts on this
okay
pretty straightforward
in the caption of figure seven two
it says
lower left negative free energy
gradients I.E prediction errors Through
Time
well
first issue it's empty
that may have been fixed in in some
subsequent like not a full reprinting
but that may have been fixed
but it's empty there
what are similarities or differences
between prediction error and free energy
gradients are they the same thing
what's the difference between free
energy and free energy gradients what is
a gradients
here I'm going to look to actually
this question which we looked at earlier
today
so this question from chapter two asked
um prediction error surprise and
variational free energy they're related
to each other but it's sometimes
confusing
and
[Music]
um
to to kind of look at this again
the best fitting model with the most
model evidence
is going to have the lowest prediction
error the lowest lowest surprise and the
lowest variational free energy but there
are subtle differences
prediction error is a simple
differential between prediction and
observation so if the prediction is 10
and the observations 11 the prediction
error is positive one
it's a it's in the units of whatever the
observations are about temperature
surprises in information theoretic
quantity
every single um
data point observation is on a
distribution is associated with some
non-zero surprise value
but it can be minimized and it's
minimized when the prediction error is
lowest
and variational free energy is described
in equation 2.5
so it's not exactly the same as surprise
but it's a bound on surprise that's kind
of the whole point
and its lowest when all of these things
are kind of in unison
and then Ali also highlighted that
surprise is what is calculated in exact
Bayesian inference
where model evidence is maximized via
surprise minimization however
where exact Bayesian inference is
intractable then we utilize approximate
Bayesian inference
and there's two ways that you could go
about doing that one approach would be a
sampling based approach
but that would be enormously
computationally costly in certain
settings and you wouldn't really know
when you've reached the right time to
stop sampling
but variational inference allows you to
approximate Bayesian inference by
bounding the surprise with a free energy
and that's the evidence lower bound
and it gets to the last piece of the
question which is what is a gradient so
a gradient is a rate of change
it could be
um on a two-dimensional
um surface
the rate of change like just a ruler at
the angle of the rate of change of that
local point you could have a gradient in
one dimension
you could have um different
dimensionalities of gradients but
basically they're the local rate of
change around some point
and so it's like if you have beliefs
about
um the temperature in the 10 and then
the observation comes in and it's 11. so
that's associated with some prediction
error some surprise and some free energy
gradient and then the gradient should
steer you towards updating your
prediction from 10 upwards
under the full attention setting you
would go from 10 all the way to 11.
under a no attention setting you
wouldn't move at all but you'd want to
move from 10 towards 11 that's the
gradient or the flow going towards 11
whereas you wouldn't want to go uphill
towards like nine
thank you Ali
cool
let's replace this in the figure
I'll do it later
okay any other thoughts on on this
a little bit unclear with the dark lines
because they're all Crossing and
everything like that
but the kind of
moral of the story is
when something happens
there's a transient
um adjustment of the model but also as
we we've discussed
um like we're in discrete time
so it's it's not immediately clear why
there's interpolated continuous
values
okay maybe this is
speaking to this
so figure seven two and seven seven
have these curves where belief updating
is happening faster and the text alludes
to some sort of simulation machine yeah
I believe that is the um the stock
machinery
of the SPM package
but I'm not exactly sure
um
yes it does include like when we just
like when we looked at the um
the SPM vbx
it has a section on um
dopamine
and I think that that is being
um
displayed in in continuous time
interpolated
but I'm not exactly sure why
that happens and I think it would be
more
[Music]
um
clear given our discrete time
setting to just show a point
Associated at each time step
does anyone have like any other like
thought on this
okay
what is factorization
in Factor graphs
in the brain and conceptually
what is anyone's thought on this
okay let's look at what
others have for it
okay
so factorization is when variables
operate uh statistically independently
from one another
so you can have the joint distribution
of let's just say A and B here but we're
not talking
um just only about the A and the B
Matrix but actually it turns out that
those are factorizable
um but here it's just being used
generically and so it allows you to
um break down the statistical joint
estimation of a comma B into
a times B so for example if you're
rolling a die and flipping a coin
you can talk about the The Joint
probability of all 12 options of heads
or tails and one through six but also
you can approach that by saying well
there's a one-half probability of heads
and a 1 6 of getting a three
so you're able to calculate the joint
distribution via separating out the coin
flip from the die because they don't
influence each other whereas if they did
influence each other
then it wouldn't be factorizable
um neurologically one of the most common
places where people discuss
factorization
is with the what and the where
stream in the brain
and the idea here is like an object's
identity
should be factorizable from its for
example location in the visual field or
size
visually
because
um
you want to be able to separate out what
something is and where it is and people
have identified these these two streams
of visual information flow that reflect
the the
um the what and the where
so I'll bring this in
but the what in the where
are these two
um of honey
bizarre
um
these two streams of visual input
some people have have kind of like
it's one of those things where it's like
the structure of the inference
architecture recapitulates the structure
of the problem
because again we would expect Vision to
have
um that kind of factorization between
what an object is and where it is
and um
here
someone has added an example about
um fruits and berries different
properties
but they're all kind of related to
ripeness
Ollie
also in terms of category Theory
factorization means that I mean every
function can be written as a kind of
composite function of a search active
function and an injective function so
you know the word the factorization
system for a given category consists of
two
um two sets of or two
um two sets of morphisms uh so one of
which
um have the ability to to contain all
the isomorphisms of the given category
and also there are closed
under the composite function so uh in a
in this sense factorization system can
give rise to the concepts some other
Concepts in category Theory such as
and also
an important uh property of
factorization system is each
factorization is itself a functorial so
uh two I mean they can be regarded as
two morphisms that can be mapped into
each other by commuting arrows or
morphisms uh so uh yeah it's one of the
important Concepts in category Theory as
it gives rise to some other Concepts
such as equivalency and orthogonality
and so on
cool thank you
one other point and the reason why
Factor graphs and factorizations are
even being discussed is um the
connections in the Bayesian graph
reflect which variables have influence
on each other
so for example o of T minus 1 is only
influenced by in the state of T minus
one
so it's like
um through the a matrix
um and similarly
and so it's not the case that all
variables have an edge to each other
first off that would cause connections
like through time which would violate
the markovian property which says that
the only way that the past can influence
the future is through the present
so that's a massively simplifying
assumption if you think about a time
series with a hundred time steps
if you enable every time step to e to be
possibly connected to every other time
step you're going to end up with
calculated out but however many hundreds
and hundreds of edges
whereas if you abide by the markovian
property
which is at least a defensible
statistical approximation if not
even more valid than that
the markovian property in time
simplifies out how many edges you have
to fit
but also there are sparseness about like
Pi doesn't reach down to influence
observations
and so that first off captures something
important and structural about the
problem we're trying to solve we don't
want to even open the door to a
opportunity for policy to just be like
changing our observations with a thumb
on the scale
nor do we want policy to Simply
intervene directly in a hidden state but
rather with the B Matrix we have policy
intervening in how hidden States change
their time so the sparseness
um relative to the all by all edges that
could exist the sparseness helps embody
the statistical and causal nature of the
problem and it's massively
computationally simplifying
so that's why factorization comes into
play
um
related factorization and the recipe of
chapter six why are there two a matrices
so let's just clarify which example
so this is probably about the maze yeah
okay
so this is about the maze on page 131.
okay okay didn't see it
um
there are two modalities that represent
extra receptive sensory data pertaining
to where
so that's just the location of the um
uh rat in the maze and also there's a
what modality
that is like am I tasting something
delicious or or not
and so just like the what in the way or
in the brain
there are two matrices
and they have different shapes
because the location the where a matrix
Maps
locations
to um location cues to location hidden
states true locations
which is here on noiseless mapping
and the second modality
maps location
[Music]
to whether there is no no tasty Q or
aversive Q
at these two locations so when when the
mouse is in the center Junction
or down on the bottom we're in this
dashed line row
and then in this example the right side
has the black circle and the left side
has the white circle
any other
thoughts or comments on this
okay
this I think this little little test
question
don't know if we left this for ourselves
or someone else's dropping test
questions for us
walk through the Section from 131 to 135
explain all the rows columns subscripts
and values
we just described a 1 and A2 matrices
columns are
[Music]
um
locations
in the A1 Matrix these are queues of
what and then in the A2 Matrix these are
what is application so where and what
this is the same except now the black is
on the left instead of on the right
and so we see that reflected with
here we have a one
and a 98 on the right and a one on the
bottom
here the one has moved up a row and the
98 is on the left
B2
is not influenced by policy one stays at
one and one stays at one
so it's kind of like a
Matrix having the diagonal
the identity Matrix for a
is kind of like the trivial
um
noiseless perception
observations just map one to one to
Hidden States and similarly
um a b Matrix with an identity diagonal
is kind of like trivial action
because if you're in this state you stay
there 100 of time and if you're in that
state you stay there 100 of the time
but that's B2 they're just getting that
out of the way they're basically saying
whatever you do
you're not changing
the structure of the problem in terms of
the the um location of the food
and and not saying um that the rat has
no control over the context
however they are going to focus in on
the the four slices
of the B Matrix
so the B Matrix is inner is
intermediating hidden States and how
they change through time so the hidden
State s is about the true location that
the rat is in so there's four locations
and the B Matrix is going to describe
um
the
the transitions in location
under the four different action policies
and so there are certain states that you
can't
um
uh well this is um
four matrices that the rat can choose
they allow for a move from any states
except for the left and right arm to any
other state
however the right and the left arms are
absorbing States the rat must stay
so here
we have the absorbing state
um here's one
if you're on the left you stay on the
left and if you're on the right
you stay on the right
and then hear whether you're here or
here you transition to going to the
right so I guess it can jump from here
to there
and
sees the preference
vector
the um
C1
is for for again the location
and this just kind of pushes it off the
starting location so it does something
and then here in the C2 is the
preference for over the context
observations like the preferring the
tasty food not the reversive
and then just note that because these
are in like
natural log kind of or they're an e to
the exponentiation
um a six
means that the attractive
um is more is e to the sixth
more rewarding or you know more
preferable
D is the prior
it has a perfect true belief about its
starting location
and regarding the context
it has a 50 50 uncertainty about the
equal probability
of the um which context it's in
but this is a good question
and I just ask
um so there we've we have the two
matrices the one and two so going back
to what we were saying earlier if you
were going to feed that into SPM 12.
would you then
um
multiply those A1 and A2 together a sort
of a chronica matrix to get some
something that was something like maybe
16 by
15 there a big Matrix and what we're
what we're saying is in this application
you are able to uh
you know the what on the where are
separable
um but to use
use spm12 you would
you'd have to
multiply these
together
um
sort of a chronic
product or um
I think we'd have to look
but my understanding is that the S true
location
um and the and the true like that that
the true awareness
would be multiplied by this a matrix to
give the where observation
and then the true context would get
multiplied by this
um
which is uninformative about which
context it's in if you're in the bottom
right here
and so this is a true context would be
emitted through A2
to the um context observation
however there's there's many situations
um speaking a little more generally
where you can
hack it into a huge single Matrix
like you could imagine there's four
locations or like just speaking of the
observations
um you could have
five locations with null reward
five with the black and five with the
white and the 15
across or you know 15 row Matrix
where every combination of location and
um
context is a unique one
yeah but that defeats the whole point of
factorization
yeah the science realization usually
more simple yeah
yeah except there may be some
interesting settings where very very
large sparse matrices
may have some um special computational
representations that actually might make
that efficient
but not in this scale
how can we read equations such as 7.8
okay this is a little bit of a general
com
um that might be better fit for the uh
math learning group
so I'll just throw it over there
and now to 7.8
we don't have the natural language
description
human written however
let us go to the AI
see how it does
okay 7.8 latex
Coda AI columns
okay this is a
um pretty
straightforward reading
the epistemic value I of Pi
is being calculated
um based upon the posterior predictive
entropy and the expected ambiguity
not very helpful explanation
this one is why would a high school
student be interested in it
they may not be interested
think higher of high school students
um
here's a column asking about where it
might be important and here's defining
the variables
so not super
helpful for exactly what we're looking
for but you know it gives a it gives a
look
but but to return to the um
question of reading it
anyone want to just pick a line and and
read how they see it
okay I won't go over beat them
but
um the epistemic values and we're just
looking at the epistemic aspect of the
equation two six
expected free energy
H is an entropy so it's describing how
blurry or peaked a distribution is
and this is about
the observation
distribution Through Time tilde
conditioned on action
so if our action is associated with very
blurry observations
then it's going to be a high entropy
whereas if the observation
[Music]
entropy is is very low
then those observations have have um
lower entropy
so if um
yeah if if we're
getting like a a broad spectrum of
observations from policy
that would have higher epistemic value
whereas like if there if you know that
every time you um open this book it's
like this it's gonna give you the same
100 time steps the same data
then it's not as informative
and here is an entropy about essentially
the a matrix
because it's discussing the relationship
between the observations conditioned
upon hidden States
um
also
being conditioned upon the policy
but this kind of goes without saying
about the conditioning of over policy
because basically everything is going to
be conditioned upon a policy because the
epistemic value is something that's
computed on a per policy
basis
here
Mutual information which uh Neil alluded
to earlier it's a very interesting
quantity especially because like it's
it's an equivalence
we have q of s given Pi on both sides
so this part is like kind of not
um changing for a given policy
and here we have
P if observations given hidden States
it's like the a matrix
relationship to
the variational posterior on
observations given policies
so again everything's conditioned on
policy so it's kind of like POS
difference or Divergence with Q of o
so if
um s
is
um
it
if the O's are the same and S doesn't
change anything
then the Divergence is low
if you can imagine if s tilde like added
nothing
conditioning on ass added nothing now
conditioning on the true temperature
the sequence of thermometer observations
was the same
then knowing the true temperature didn't
help you at all
so the mutual information
would be
um low
whereas if knowing
the hidden States
were to provide information
[Music]
then P of O conditioned on S
would differ from Q of o
I I I'm not 100 confident on any of
these readings I'm just kind of just
saying them
and this last one
is um again after you kind of ignore the
pies here
it's Q of s q of s condition on
observations
so if the observations
are meaningless then this term is zero
whereas if the observations do matter
conditioning on o does matter
then there is
[Music]
um
a positive Information Gain
and I'm not exactly sure what
this little supplement is adding
other than describing the factorization
relationship it's saying the variational
distribution of hidden States Through
Time condition on policy and
observations
so kind of like our inference about true
temperature depending on what we do and
the observations from the thermometer is
defined as equal sign with a triangle
and here's essentially a factorization
probably derivable from the Bayesian
theorem and the sparsity of the
generative model
POS is like the a matrix
Q of s given Pi is basically the B
Matrix
and then this is
um the downstairs bit
which was seen up here Ali
foreign
yeah well if I may give a kind of a more
informal reading of this equation so uh
here uh well this equation basically
means that uh both I mean extrinsic and
epistemic value uh work together to
somehow increase uh the
um the likelihood of our preferred
outcomes uh with by minimizing the
uncertainty so for example that the
extrinsic value
depends on the posterior predictive
entropy as in as shown in the first
slide
and which is which can only be
informative if the agent can be certain
about a current state or its current
state so it means that epistemic
uncertainty
should first be resolved before uh I
mean any kind of action or any kind of
utility uh that will come into play
and also at the same time
if the agent
is
confident enough in its current estate
it shouldn't uh somehow
undertake uh or or perform in a kind of
epistemic actions that would seek to
pursue a kind of successful plan so
and especially this is related to the
Explorer Explorer exploitation
exploration dilemma so briefly uh as
also we talked about in the previous
session uh well minimizing free energy
corresponds directly to approximate
Bayesian inference
by choosing the least
surprising outcomes so if the if the
agents could somehow model their
environments they need to have posterior
beliefs about the amount of the control
they have upon the state transitions
producing those outcomes in other words
we need to somehow take into
consideration the posterior beliefs
about those control states which
by turn
relies on prior beliefs about to those
controlled outcomes
so
um yeah I mean by using this kind of
principled way of
resolving the uncertainties
or in other words resolving the uh the
prior uncertainties based on the control
states that can minimize the expected
free energy we can somehow achieve
a theory that's that can provide a
formal definition for that epistemic
value or the value of the information we
can gain from the situation
and also um
it it somehow
focuses uh the
um
the importance of the purposeful
behavior that also that also relies on
the generative models that generate
those uh or
um
consider those future outcomes
so this is basically the formulation
that
includes or unifies uh some of the uh
perspectives or pre-established
perspectives such as the KL control
theory and
many other previously established
perspectives and approaches
so uh in case anyone wants to further
explore
the derivation of epistemic value and
the implications of it I highly
recommend one of the earlier
papers by friston at all namely active
inference and epistemic value from 2015.
oh awesome thanks
it's 10 2015.
great I'll I'll add it in here
yeah
a lot of uh oh we know pragmatic value
unlike reward maximization our active
inference concept of pragmatic value is
the alignment between preferences and
observations
so that does the kind of Kernel work
of
preference satisfaction and homeostasis
and then epistemic value
depending on the um
sophistication of the the generative
model and what other features it
contains like learning and nested
structure attention and so on epistemic
value does a ton of work
and that's
exactly
what we point to as what is missing in
for example reward learning
two huge issues first off it works well
when you know what the reward function
is but discovering it is an issue
and even when you do and if you do
Discover it or uh a proxy or heuristic
or however you want to think about it
all you've really done is just coerced a
shoehorned different components of
epistemic value
into the currency of pragmatic reward
so with equation 2.6 and expected free
energy
we get to
delineate
epistemic and pragmatic value
and then the the the challenge of
parameterizing these models is to
balance them
for example if the preference Vector of
the mat of the maze was
six six one billionths and negative then
maybe it's not as big of a deal in
comparison to the epistemic value and in
contrast where the preference is is you
know 100 million versus negative 100
million you see more overall
pragmatically oriented behavior so
expectation pursuing aversion
um repulsing
foreign
interesting chapter
learning
more technical details some equations
that we haven't always
um gone through but I I again I hope we
for all of these equations that we end
up with
natural language
and pseudo code and code representations
um more examples that are just sort of
briefly touched upon
massive topics like structure learning
just being essentially alluded to
and hierarchically nested models in this
case a discrete time and a discrete time
model you can tell because of the -1 t t
plus one little figure 4.3 fractional
figure 4.3
and then another kind of
um discrete State space discrete time
but here nested model
it's kind of like a a 3-4 song like one
two three two two three
with this nested time scale
that's seven
well
next week we
um turn to eight continuous time
I think that we've um hopefully surfaced
a lot of opportunities for improvements
of the um questions and discourse code
equations explanations and so on
because seven definitely is uh
moving lightly through multiple examples
and results and topics
and and so I think there could be a lot
of good work with us
um sweeping our Trail
and adding questions that we wish would
have been asked or would have been added
to uh connect the dots
and then chapter 8 is going to head into
the continuous time setting
and close on Hybrid models which have
continuous and discrete time components
before chapter 9 goes into the model a
database modeling
and chapter 10 concludes it so
thanks everyone great times
looking forward to uh yes see you at the
uh but the alternative or whatever time
next week on Lucky 7-Eleven
okay that's great thank you
farewell bye